{"Argentina": {"code": "AR", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e21?prd=OCC19", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "13/07/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "11/05/2023"}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes. However, not specifically Covid-19 responsive. This declaration did not have significant legal effects - more to administration of financial resources.", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "It was unclear whether rule-making authority was unlocked by law 27,541 or was an exercise of the president's constitutional authority to issue DNUs.", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "To the extent it was accepted there was a declaration, it was contained in a statute. The extension of those declarations had parliamentary approval but not through substantial changes,", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "The December 2019 declaration of emergency was extended by DNU 260 in March 2020, for 1 year.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 12, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "No - There was no new general statute law introduced to respond to Covid-19 in particular.  [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes but important legal questions regarding presidential use of powers [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "Yes, but de facto [Part II.A]. The Constitutional bill of rights was not formally suspended under a constitutional state of siege. However, the president/government derogated from the American Convention on Human Rights and the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights, indicating the government's view that human rights were suspended during  (at least early stages of) the pandemic.", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Postponed - In 2020, only local elections had to be held during the pandemic. Two small municipal elections in Córdoba and Santa Fe were postponed in March and May due to the public health measures. Río Cuarto (a city of around 140,000 inhabitants) finally voted in November 2020. San Guillermo (a small town of 9,000) has not been able to hold its elections yet) [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Municipal elections, Río Cuarto, Córdoba province, Argentina* (29 November 2020) and Legislative elections, Argentina* (14 November 2021)", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes [Part IV.A.1]. On 19 March 2020, the federal government implemented the ‘social, preventive, and compulsory isolation’ (ASPO), and imposed a wide range of strict mobility restrictions on citizens throughout Argentina.", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Yes. On 31 March 2020, the ASPO restrictions were prolonged up until 12 April 2020. ASPO lasted until November 7 2020 (DNU 875) under slightly more relaxed rules  [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Severe interruption and suspension of activities: Congress was inactive for two months and remained closed for weeks [Part III.B]. More than a month after the imposition of public health measures, the opposition asked to resume activities. Congress resumed regular activities on 13 May 2020.", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part III.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Yes. There was scrutiny, but weak. Time delay: revisions usually when the regulations already expired. The Bicameral Committee first met in May 2020 to decide upon a package of around 20 DNUs decreed in the previous months, related to the pandemic. None of the several Covid-19 DNUs have been repealed since the pandemic began and none are subject to sunset clauses.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "No amendment possible (for DNUs) [Part III.A].", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes, added by government.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "Yes - notified to the UN and regional OAS authorities [Part II.A], ACHR and ICCPR", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Austria": {"code": "AT", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e28", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "30/06/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "13/03/2023"}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No emergency declarations.", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "NA [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "NA [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "Basic constitutional changes were not made but there was a minimal change to the text to the constitutiont o allow government meetings online and meetings of municipal councils.  ", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "Yes. These were mostly created by omnibus bills, 22 of which were explicitly named ‘Covid-19-statute’ between March and August 2020. In particular, the Covid-19 Measures Act [Part II.B].", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": 1, "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "Yes, in the passing of bills (criticisms regarding sped up processes and lack of public consultation, but no challenges) [Part II.B].", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "Yes it did. in some cases, the parliamentary procedure was sped up even more by MPs introducing a bill with minimum contents (‘carrier rocket’, CR) which was profoundly amended in the competent parliamentary committee [Part II.B]. CRs are bills introduced by MPs or Government but intended to be heavily amended during passage, primarily in the competent parliamentary committee. The basis for CRs is that the ministry doesn't need to provide all the content in the draft. In this case, the CR was introduced by the Government. The majority of CR bills were not used to modify the omnibuss bills. Notably, the opposition did not have a majority.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "Yes, for the Covid-19-Measures Act (initially 31  December 2020, was renewed until 30 June 2021 and then amended by Parliament to last until 31 December 2021) [Part II.B]. Some amendments to the infectious Diseases Act, which had sunset clauses and whose periods were harmonised with the durations specified in the Covid-19 Measures Act.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No but restrictions [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Postponed (one election to the state parliament and three local elections) [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": " Styrian municipal elections, Austria*  (28 June 2020)", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Yes (10 days renewable) [Part III.A].", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown in activities: no interruption (parliamentary work was not disrupted, nor on the federal nor on the state level, nor in plenary sessions nor in committee sessions) [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "NA. ", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B and C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Yes, but only on an exceptional basis - In principle, no, unless the statute in question that empowers the making the regulation specifies that Parliament has a say in making the regulation. It is possible, but rarely done. In the case of stay at home orders, the new act specifies that the permission to make a stay at home order is required before it can come into force. As from September 2020, the Main Committee of the National Council required, by an amendment of relevant legislation, the Federal Minister of Health to seek explicit consent by the central parliamentary committee before issuing certain public health ordinances, including stay-at-home ordinances (for details, see Part III.A).", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "No, Parliament cannot amend regulations. However, for some regulations, in particular stay at home, the Covid-19 measures act (statute) required that the Parliament gave its conset before. ", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes (for stay-at-home orders 10 days and four weeks for bans on entering certain premises) [Part III.A]. ", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Belgium": {"code": "BE", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/e1.013.1/law-occ19-e1?prd=OCC19", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "23/12/2020"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "13/03/2023"}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "No, then Yes [Part II.A]. Pandemic act came into force in Oct/2021. Immediately, the executive made a declaration, which was later confirmed by Parliament and extended multiple times.", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "No, until Oct 2021. Yes, after [Part II.A] - special powers granted by Parliament.", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "Yes, there was a parliamentary confirmation under the Pandemic Act 2021.", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes, the declaration had a maximum period of 3 months. ", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 3, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A]", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A]", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No [Part I]", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "Yes", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "Yes - for two Special Powers Acts adopted on 27 March 2020 (6 days) [Part II.B]. However, these Special Powers Acts are not limited to Covid-19", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": 6, "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "No, the authors mention in general broad parliamentary support in the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute. However, the situation is different to the act in 2021, which had great political opposition.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "No - At the federal level, two Special Powers Acts were adopted on 27 March 2020, with broad parliamentary support [Part II.B]", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "Yes - a sunset provision conditioning its effects to the continuation of the WHO declaration of a PHEIC [Part II.B]. It lasted for 3 months and was not renewed.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "No - the crisis has not led to the postponement of any national, regional, or local elections in Belgium. \nThe crisis has, nonetheless, interfered with the electoral calendar by excluding the option of elections at the federal level in the spring of 2020. This was one of the options explored by political actors and in public debate to put an end to the political deadlock in Belgium which had existed since December 2018. \nTo note: apart from the issue of legislative elections, two significant ballots were postponed due to the Covid-19 pandemic. Firstly, the election of judicial members of the High Council of Justice was postponed to 25 September 2020. Secondly, the social elections process was also disrupted. Social elections are held every four years to elect the workers’ representatives in the Works Council and/or Committees for Prevention and Protection at Work. These elections were due to take place from 11–24 May 2020 but were first suspended, and later rescheduled to 16–29 November 2020. Distance voting was used [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "None", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "No sunset provision mentioned in the regulation: the Ministerial Decree of 30 April 2020 made the obligation to remain at home less stringent from 4 May 2020, by recommending online working instead of making it compulsory [Part IV.A.1].However, the decrees were updated regularly, based on scientific advice and evolution of the pandemic.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Mild interruption with important slowdown at the beginning of the pandemic: it affected parliamentary activities but Parliament could legally continue to operate for 'essential activities'. There was a considerable slowdown from mid-March to mid-April 2020 (select committees did not meet, but the plenary did), then activities resumed in a more normal fashion [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, however legal opinion on legality of draft regulations given by the Councel of State from Jan 2021, but were exempted from this requirement before.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes, possible [Part II.B and C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Yes - No automatic confirmation of public health regulations by Parliament, however Parliament can vote to repeal any regulation at any time after it comes into force. Following the passage of the Pandemic Act 2021, it was decided not to create a process of legislative confirmation of regulations because this would have made such regulations primary legislation whose validity could only be tested in the Constitutional Court.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Not explicity, but as Parliament can repeal regulations it can also amend them. However, would turn them into primary legislation when doing so.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Prior to Oct 2021, Yes for special powers decrees only (to be confirmed within one year or they lapse); for most public health interventions regulations not subject to sunset period. After Oct 2021, all regulations subject to the sunset period not exceeding the emergency declaration period (maximum 3 months). ", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Chile": {"code": "CL", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e5", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "04/01/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "13/03/2023"}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes (state of catastrophe by reason of public calamity - 18 March 2020) [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes - for both the state of catastrophe [Part II.A] and Decree 4 [Part II.C]. ", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No [Part II.A]. However, Art. 41 of the Constitution provides that if the constitutional state of catrastrophe is extended for more than a year, subsequent extensions require congressional approval. 2 extensions were subject to a vote (March and June 2021).", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes - The statutory declaration of emergency under art. 36 Sanitary Code is not subject to a statutory sunset provision. However, the Presidential Decree itself introduced a sunset clause, which has been amended a number of times by Presidential Decree to extend the original declaration and powers granted.  [Part II.A].", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 3, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes - See Decree 4 of 2020 declared a statutory state of public health emergency as provided by Art. 36 of the Sanitary Code. The declaration enabled the President to delegate powers to the under secretary for Public Health, as described in the report [Part II.C].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "Congress passed a constitutional amendment to authorise the withdrawal of pension funds [Part V.A]. In addition, there were a series of constitutional amendments, mostly related with the constituent process. However, no amendments concerning the emergency powers enabling framework.", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No. However, there were three minor pieces of primary legislation modifying the Sanitary Code.", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA. However, significant political gridlock and controversy over the response to the economic crisis created by the coronavirus. There were pieces of legislation providing economic relief packages passed against the government's will [Part V.A]. ", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No - only mentions restrictions but no general suspension [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Postponed - for the constitution-making process - the first stage of the process was a plebiscite to be held on 26 April 2020, in which the citizens were to be asked whether they wanted a new Constitution. The electoral process in general was postponed for at least six months. Law 21,221, published on 26 March 2020, amended the Constitution to indicate that the first plebiscite in the constitution-making process was to take place six months later, on 25 October, and postponed local government and regional government elections to April 2021. Elections to members of the constituent assembly and local government elections, originally postponed to April 2021, had to be postponed again for May 2021, due to Covid reasons (Law 21,324). No other elections have been postponed on public health grounds during the pandemic. On 25 October 2020, the referendum was finally held [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Referendum, Chile* (25 October 2020), Presidential and Parliamentary elections, Chile (21 November 2021)", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes - 'dynamic quarantines' [Part IV.A.1]. Later, dynamic quarantines would be replaced by a tiered system ('step by step plan'). However, curfews between 10 pm and 5 am would continue until October 2021", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Mobility restrictions have partially overlapping enabling provisions. There is a night curfew imposed by means of the powers granted by the constitutional state of emergency, subject to sunset clause. On the other hand, there are mobility restrictions that operate during the day, enacted by means of the powers granted by the Sanitary Code, which are not subject to a statutory sunset clause. ", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown in activities: Parliament was in operation all pandemic (through virtual meetings) [Part III.B]. There were no complaints.", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "Yes for Decree 4 (the Office of the Comptroller-General (exclusively on legal grounds) can review the legality of decrees) [Part II.C]. No (not mentioned for the state of catastrophe). ", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes - courts cannot review a declaration of a state of exception but judicial review for particular measures is possible [Part III.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "No  [Part III.A].", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "No [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "Yes - from the ACHR, in respect to Article 15 (freedom of assembly) and Article 22 (freedom of movement) [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Costa Rica": {"code": "CR", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e41", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "31/12/2022"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "18/04/2023"}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No - Declarations are supported under the National Law on Emergency and Risk Prevention, and endorsement by the Assembly is not required [Part II.A].", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "No [Part II.B]. Article 180 discusses constitutional emergencies. It does not elaborate on the conditions for a declaration of emergency - the law comes in and specifies much of the addition.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Yes (no suspension of elections, but suspension of all referenda on 2 April 2020 - municipal elections were held, but referenda ultimately not held) [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "General elections, Costa Rica (6 February 2022)", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "No - only for people infected or suspected of infection, and vehicle restrictions on private vehicles [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown (In March 2020, there was a very brief break in its regular operations when the Assembly was relocated to a nearby museum so that its meetings would comply with the social distancing protocols but minimal. On 7 October 2020, after a very long delay, a much larger, new parliament building was opened that provided all legislative committees the necessary space to work.  However, on 20 October 2020, an outbreak of Covid-19 in the Assembly interrupted the committees’ sessions for nine days [Part III.B]).", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No - ex post [Part III.C].", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part III.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "No.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Public policies being imposed periodically. Vehicle and commerce activities needed to be continued.  The lengh depended on whether the Covid index was high or low.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Finland": {"code": "FI", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e32", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "03/09/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "22/03/2023"}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - twice [Part II.A]", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes (until the Communicable Diseases Act was amended so that there would be no need to declare new states of emergency) [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "Yes - decrees related to state of emergencies must be submitted to the Parliament and the Parliament discusses the decree in a single reading instead of two [Part III.A].", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes - 6 months sunset provision [Part II.C]. The government declared two emergencies: the first one lasted 3 months (16 March 2020 to 15 June 2020), while the second lasted 2 (1 March 2021 to 27 April 2021).", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 6, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "Declarations of a state of emergency can be made both in terms of section 23 of the Constitution and in terms of the Emergency Powers Act. In both contexts, a pandemic is a legitimate ground for such a declaration. The two states of emergency that were actually declared in Finland were in terms of the Emergency PowersAct (16 March to 15 June 2020, and 1 March to 27 April 2021). Nevertheless, constitutional emergency powers were used even if there was no formal declaration in this context.", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes - under the Emergency Powers Act [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes but some lack of clarity that arose regarding the relationship between the emergency procedures under section 23 of the Constitution and the terms of the Emergency Powers Act. [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "No.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No - but restrictions [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Yes, postponed - municipal elections were initially scheduled to be held on 18 April 2021 and finally happened on 13 June 2021 - with advance voting taking place between 26 May and 8 June 2021 [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Local elections, Finland* (14 June 2021), County elections, Finland  (23 January 2022)", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "No - guidance only [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "No. However, light interruption with light slowdown: no interruption but parliamentary proceedings concerning non-urgent matters were postponed (March 2020- Sep 2020 and twice in March and April 2021) and restrictions of the number of MPs in plenary sessions  [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No - ex  post [Part II.C]. ", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes - under section 106 and 107 of the Constitution courts are empowered to find both secondary and primary legislation to be unlawful or unconstitutional, though review of primary legislation under section 106 is very rare and disputes are resolved ordinarily through interpretation.  Also, there is a distinction between finding regulations 'illegal' and 'unconstitutional.' [Part II.C and III.C]. Crucially, Section 106 (primacy of the constitution) of the constitution is rarely used by the Courts. Possible contradictions between statutes and the bill of rights are usually resolved by interpretation.", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "No. During the Covid-19 pandemic, four interpellations have so far been addressed to the Parliament. None of them has concerned the Covid-19 measures taken by the Government [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "No [Part II.A]", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes - maximum 6 months sunset provision (depends on the validity of the main Decree) [Part II.C]. No sunset provisions for regular decrees [Part III.A].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "France": {"code": "FR", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e9", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "08/03/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "09/03/2023"}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - 'state of health emergency' [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "Yes. Whenever this legal regime is used, Parliament must be informed and can demand any complementary information to scrutinize it [Part II.B]. The initial Declaration can be made without parliament, but after a month it needs to be approved an extension, and then a statute needs to be enacted. Approval was quick to gain legitimacy.", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes - According to the PHC, the state of health emergency can be decreed for a duration of one month, after which it can only be extended by the Parliament for a duration fixed in the new statute. However, this was not the case in March 2020 insofar as Statute n° 2020-290 derogated from the PHC by declaring the state of health emergency for two months. [Part II.B].", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 1, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No, by statute [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes - by statute [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes but disruption to the equilibrium [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "Yes", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "Yes - for the adoption of Statute n° 2020-290 declaring the state of emergency [Part II.B] (4 days), for the adoption of a bill extending the state of emergency [Part II.C], for the adoption of ordinances and of various statutes [Part II.C].", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": 4, "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "No [Part II.B].  Opposition parties did not strongly oppose the declaration of the state of health emergency, though some human rights and civil society organizations did. However, parliamentary opposition was strong in the extensions of the emergency.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "No. However, in the committee there are deputies from many parties.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "No sunset provision for the whole statute [Part III.A]", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No - but restrictions [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Yes, postponed - municipal elections were planned on 15 March and 22 March 2020, to elect mayors and city councils. Lockdown led to postponement of the 22 March 2020 elections. The second ballot was then planned on 28 June 2020. Besides municipal elections, the election of six senators representing French people living abroad was postponed by a year. The mandate of the six senators, which was supposed to be terminated, was also extended to 30 September 2020. [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "first round of local elections in France (15 March 2020), second round of local elections, France* (28 June 2020), Senate election (indirect), France (27 September 2020), ", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes - France declared a national lockdown (stay-at-home requirement) on 16 March 2020. This was implemented by Decree n° 2020-260 [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Yes.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Mild interruption with important slowdown in activities: Parliament was initially in recess from 9 to 22 March 2020, but access to parliamentary premises was restricted from 17 March 2020 until the end of June [Part III.B]. As a consequence, presidents of parliamentary groups were allowed to vote on behalf of their MPs. Except for committees, no meetings were held online and the authors note that it was impossible to preserve real parliamentary debate.", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No - it should nevertheless be noted that in the case of the first bill extending the state of health emergency, the President used his right to seize the CC (aimed at increasing the legitimacy of such a decision). With regards to ordinances, lack of ex ante constitutional scrutiny (exacerbated during the crisis) [Part II.C]. However, F=for the statute, there was an ex-ante judicial review. Mostly because the government was seeking for more legitimacy.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes, and cases regarding public health measures have been brought before courts by civil society organisations [Part II.B]. Regulatory measures can all be reviewed by a judge [Part II.C]. ", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Under Article 37 of the Constitution, the Parliament does not interfere with and therefore does not scrutinize the regulation-making powers of Government. Therefore, public health regulations were not subject to parliamentary scrutiny [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Hong Kong": {"code": "HK", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e8", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "15/10/2020"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "21/03/2023"}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "No - not a formal declaration at least [Part II.A] but rather a 'state of affairs' [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "No - as the legal framework is used according to a state of affairs rather than according to a declaration of public health emergency [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "NA [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "No - but the aforementioned state of affairs triggers statutes and decree powers under the relevant statutes [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No - not in principle [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Postponed (the Chief Executive in Council decided to postpone the Legislative Council General Election from 6 September 2020 to 5 September 2021. The Chief Executive in Council exercised her powers under the Emergency Regulations Ordinance to make the Emergency (Date of General Election) (Seventh Term of the Legislative Council) Regulation, effective 1 August 2020). Constitutional status of this decision dubious [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Legislative Council elections, Hong Kong*, SAR of China (19 December 2021)", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes - only at the local level [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Mild interruption with important slowdown in activities: a meeting was held on 15 February 2020 to deal with urgent Covid-19-related matters, but significant periods of the pandemic fell within recess periods; for instance, the Legislative Council did not meet between July and October 2020 but it was the summer recess, and committees continued their work. Meetings could nevertheless be adjourned / cancelled / abbreviated if needed [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes, possible [Part IV.A].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Amendment technically possible (although very rare) (for subsidiary legislation measures) [Part II.C].", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Indonesia": {"code": "ID", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e36?prd=OXCON", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "28/09/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "16/03/2023"}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "No [Part II.A]. However, a 'situation of concern' was declared under article 50 of BNPB regulation 13A,  which empowered the BNPB to obtain more resources to manage the situation but not to impose public health restrictions on the population. ", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes but tensions [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No, but the Financial Policy and Omnibus Act was pushed through.", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No - not in principle [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Postponed (Indonesia had planned to carry out elections for a large number of local government positions on 23 September 2020. On 17 March 2020 the Electoral Oversight Commission (Bawaslu) recommended the Electoral Commission to map out the various districts’s readiness to hold elections during Covid-19, with the Government initially optimistic with its initial September plans. By 25 March 2020 the Electoral Commission advised the President that an Interim Emergency Regulation was required to postpone elections. The Government, legislature and Electoral Commission agreed to delay elections on 30 March 2020; three options were initially proposed, these being 9 December 2020, 17 March 2021, or 29 September 2021. On 14 April 2020 it was agreed that elections were to be delayed by three months to from the original schedule, to be held on 9 December 2020, and the Interim Emergency Regulation (Number 2/2020) to that effect was issued on 5 May 2020. Elections were held on 9 December 2020) [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Regional elections, Indonesia* (9 December 2020)", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes - at the state and city levels - Initially, 18 areas (two provinces and 16 regencies/cities) enacted large-scale social distancing measures beginning in April 2020, reduced to seven areas in September 2020. [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Yes for some of local stay at home provisions. ", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown in activities: business as usual [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "No.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "No. However, amendment possible for Parliamentary acts.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes. However, BNPB \"certain emergency\" is extendable by head of BNPB", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No.", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Israel": {"code": "IL", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e13", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "14/04/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "31/03/2023"}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - Constitutional Covid-related Emergency Regulations were issued under the Basic Law: The Government. However, a state of emergency was not specially declared in the context of the pandemic, but had instead been in existence (and annually renewed) since the foundation of the modern state of Israel in 1948. Furthermore, a number of statutory emergencies were declared. Later, a new declaration under the Covid law. Also under the public health emergency [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "Yes - The general emergency declaration under The Basic Law: The Govenrment is made by the parliament.  The other statutory emergencies were made by the Government but approved by the Knesset. From July 2020, the Coronalaw provided that a declaration of emergency was limited to 45 days and needed to be communicated to a parliamenary committee as soon as possible. If the government wishes to extend beyond 45 days, it requires the approval of the parliamentary committee or the plenary of the Knesset. The Knesset could nullify a declaration at any time.  ", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes - The entry into force of the Corona Law automatically triggered a declaration of emergency, which lasted 45 days [Part II.B]", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 1, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "Yes - general emergency it is made under a Constitutional [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes - Based on the PHO, the Minister of Health issued a declaration on 27 January 2020 declaring Covid-19 as a dangerous contagious disease which may create a severe risk to public health, thus invoking the ‘emergency powers’. [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "There were changes to the Constition - mainly related to budget-, but not directly related to Covid. Because of the political crisis. Also, there was a change in the preference in using statutory rather than constitutional arrangements.", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "Yes", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "Yes - for the adoption of the Corona Law [Part II.B]. It received a waiver from the requirement of tabling the bill for 2 days between the committee stage and the second reading. Besides, the Speaker and the Knesset Committee held that the second reading would be conducted under special procedures under section 98 of the Knesset rules of procedure, which enable limiting debate. This is perhaps the closest and most official equivalent of fast-tracking in Israel.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": 37, "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "Yes - the Corona Law was very controversial and prompted petitions to the HCJ [Part II.B]. Pre-enactment opposition along party lines, but the Bill was passed. Post-enactment criticism including unsuccessful court challenge. The enactment of the Corona Law was controversial. It was argued that it awards the government too much legislative power, with insufficient parliamentary supervision. The law passed with a vote of 48 to 35 (out of 120 members).", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "No. While the opposition did propose many many amendments (around 480), none of them were accepted. ", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No - but there were some limitations [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "No - Parliamentary elections to the 23rd Knesset were held on 2 March 2020. The next legislative elections, to the 24th Knesset, were held on 23 March 2021. Given the more complex Covid-19 situation, these elections were expected to be more complicated but the elections went smoothly and the pandemic did not disrupt the them [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "legislative elections in Israel (2 March 2020), Parliament elections,  Israel  (23 March 2021).", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes - The first national ‘lockdown’ was imposed on 25 March 2020, using an ER anchored in Basic Law: The Government [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Yes, specific end date.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown in activities: despite the unsuccesful efforts of the executive to shutdown the Knesset, it continued to meet regularly (physically) [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A and B; Part III.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Yes The government must consider alternatives to the measures taken, and the impact of the measures on civil rights and on the economy. They can be, depending on the type of regulation, in force for a maximum of 7, 14, or 28 days, when they lapse unless extended by the government. The regulations must be submitted to a Knesset committee, which can approve or reject them within 24 hours. If the committee takes no action within 24 hours, the regulations will enter into force. Thereafter, the committee can still scrutinize them and approve or reject them within 14 day [Part II.B].", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B and C].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Italy": {"code": "IT", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e11", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "11/01/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "16/03/2023"}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes, 'state of emergency' [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes. The state of emergency was first declared through a declaration of the Council of Ministers (II.B) on 31 January 2020 (which also stated that the state of emergency would have lasted for six months following said declaration). The state of emergency was then extended until 15 October 2020, 31 January 2021, 30 April 2021, 31 July 2021, 31 December 2021, and 31 March 2022. The state of emergency lasted for a total of 26 months, and was renewed 6 times.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 6, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes but tensions [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "Yes - Although Statutory Decree no 19 began as an executive rule (statutory decree, decretti lege), it was confirmed by Parliament and became the general legal framework used to make and impose public health interventions. It therefore functioned as the general framework statutory response, and was subsequently amended by later statutory decrees, both by government and in the process of transposition [Part II.B].  ", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "No. However, the process of transposing statutory decrees into Acts of Parliament enjoys per se an accelerated parliamentary passage to the extent it cannot last more than 60 days [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "No, rather cooperative - but some complaints about the lack of communication between Parliament and the Government [Part III.A] and about the potential abuse of executive measures [Part II.B].", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "Yes - The Chamber of deputies approved 67 amendments in total, 21 of which were introduced by the opposition. No amendments were voted in the Senate as the government posed a question of confidence on the entire bill (as approved by the lower House). Further, amendments approved at committee stage were substantial and many of them were indeed introduced by the opposition. ", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "Yes - THe statutory decree no 19 was not itself subject to a sunset clause but it would only operate for as long as the particular Covid-19 declaration of emergency was in force, and that declaration was subject to a sunset period and required renewing by subsequent statutory decrees [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Yes, postponed - The referendum for the confirmation of the constitutional law aiming to reduce by one-third the members of Parliament was scheduled for 29 March 2020. The call for the referendum was revoked by a decree of the President of the Republic on 5 March 2020, and it was later rescheduled to take place on 20–21 September 2020. Elections for seven Regions, 955 Municipalities, and two parliamentary seats (by-elections) were also postponed to 20–21 September 2020 [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Regional elections and constitutional referendum, Italy* (20-21 September 2020)", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "No. The stay at home orders could not last longer than the emergency declaration period, which was however renewed continuously across 2020 until March 2022.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Mild interruption with important slowdown in activities: there were significant limitations and disruptions but the Parliament's operations were never entirely suspended (although plenary sittings were reduced). Committees could meet online but not the plenary. There were also important restrictions for the activity of standing committees [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Yes - for statutory decrees but not for PM decrees.  In general, data collected between 23 February and 17 July 2020 confirms Parliament’s ability to amend and influence the decree-making powers of the government: Parliament ratified 15 statutory decrees and approved 860 amendments, with significant inflation of the content of the transposed acts compared to the original statutory decree [Part III.A].", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Amendments possible (for decretti-legge, since they are transposed into bills by one of the two houses thereafter) [Part II.B].", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes - there were sunset periods for the public health regulations contained in the PM decrees, which were the instrument in which the vast bulk of public health measures were contained.  In Statutory Decree No.19, the initial sunset period was set to 30 days.  This was later amended, to extend the sunset period for PM decrees to 50 days. [Part II.B].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Jamaica": {"code": "JM", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e26", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "30/03/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "17/03/2023"}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - 'designation of a disaster area' [Part II.B]. All hazards framework - general civil contingencies framework.", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes - upon designation of a disaster area by the Prime Minister [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No parliamentary control [Part II.A]", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "No", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes but increase in delegated legislation [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Both held in advance and postponed. National elections held 6 months early, during the height of the pandemic as it favored the incumbent government. Local elections were due November 2020 - were not held and haven't been held as of March 2023. On 11 August 2020, the Prime Minister announced that general elections would be held on 3 September 2020, six months before the end of the Government’s five year term. The timing of the elections and its implications for public health gave rise to significant public debate, especially because there was a a spike in Covid-19 infections following two major public holidays in early August. [Part III.D]).", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Parliamentary elections, Jamaica (3 September 2020)", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "No - only for older people, and curfews [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown in activities: Parliament continued to meet regularly, and several committees met regularly during the pandemic [Part III.B]. Parliament was recalled ahead from recess for the parliamentary general elections.", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "No - The only parliamentary oversight afforded in the DRMA orders so far has been voluntary [Part III.A]. However, there was parliamentary accountability for the handling of the pandemic, throughout; and during this process, the opposition argued strenuously that public health regulations should not be used to provide new crimes.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "No. However, The only parliamentary oversight afforded in the DRMA orders so far has been voluntary. Since April 2020, the Prime Minister brought the new measures before Parliament and gave parliamentarians an opportunity to ask questions and offer comments. In some instances, those discussions led to amendments to the orders and the amended form was gazetted. However, scrutiny of the pandemic measures was impaired by the failure on several occasions to circulate copies of the relevant DRMA order to parliamentarians prior to the discussion in Parliament.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes [Part II.C]. Sometimes sunset periods were added by Government, but the DRMA does not impose sunset periods for public health regulations. However, the government voluntarily added.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No.", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Latvia": {"code": "LV", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e31", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "24/05/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "27/03/2023"}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - 'emergency situation' [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "Yes - The Cabinet is obligated to notify its decision on an emergency situation or amendments to that decision—for instance, if additional restrictions of rights are necessary or if it is necessary to extend the declared emergency situation—to the Presidium of the Saeima (a political body with political representation) —a supervisory body that is elected by the Saeima and consists of five Members of Parliament (MPs): the Speaker, two Deputy Speakers, the Secretary, and the Deputy Secretary—within 24 hours of taking such decision... So far, the Saeima has approved all the decisions, including the proposed restrictions, made by the Cabinet regarding the pandemic [Part II.B]", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 3, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes but tensions [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "Yes", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "Yes (for draft law ‘On Measures for the Prevention and Suppression of Threat to the State and Its Consequences Due to the Spread of Covid-19' - 1 day; and for draft law ‘On the Operation of State Authorities During the Emergency Situation Related to the Spread of Covid-19’ - 2 days). Also for two other laws in June 2020 [Part II.B]. Note more generally. If the Parliament votes to use a fast-track procedure it can do so. And this procedure was used to overrule or amend Cabinet public health regulations.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": 1, "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "No, but important critics regarding the Law on Covid-19 Management [Part II.B].", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "No.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "No [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No - restrictions [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Postponed (neither parliamentary elections, nor local government elections were planned in 2020. However, on 13 February 2020 the Saeima adopted the Law on Dissolution of the Riga City Council. Extraordinary elections were originally scheduled to take place on 25 April 2020. Due to the emergency situation and the restrictions imposed to reduce spread of Covid-19 the elections were postponed to 6 June and later to 29 August 2020 when the Riga City Council elections took place) [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Local snap elections for city council in Riga, Latvia* (29 August 2020), Municipal Council elections, Latvia (5 June 2021)", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Yes.  Due to an extreme increase in cases during the second emergency situation, the Cabinet introduced weekend stay-at-home orders (mājsēde) during the New Year holidays (30 December 2020–4 January 2021) and on the following Friday and Saturday nights from 10pm to 5am, lasting until 7 February 2021 [Part IV.A.1]", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown in activities: there was a break from the regular session from 13 March 2020 until 9 April 2020, but work continued through extraordinary meetings and through the work of committees. From 16 May 2020, complete shift to remote work [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A and B].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "No. Although there is no formal veto power, a committee designated by the Saeima, may suggest that the Cabinet reviews the intended restrictions on rights of persons, in case less restrictive measures can be implemented for prevention of Covid-19 risks. Accordingly, the Saeima required the Cabinet to review the requirement of mask use in primary schools on 21 December 2020 and 4 March 2021. The Saeima can and will also pass laws that overrule the Cabinet.  For example, following the extensive campaigning of restaurants and cafes for the opening of outdoor terraces, on 29 April 2021 the Saeima overruled the restriction of the Cabinet by permitting the opening of outdoor terraces as of 7 May 2021 [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "No, however the Saeima can pass new laws that overrule Cabinet regulations and substitute new rules.  This power can and was exercised.  The reality is that the power of the Parliament in this regard was very dynamic. Note more generally. If the Parliament votes to use a fast-track procedure it can do so. And this procedure was used to overrule or amend Cabinet public health regulations.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes. In fact some public health regulations made by the Cabinet were not time-bound because it depends on the parent Act conferring the powers. However, many of the most important public health interventions were issued under the 'emergency situation' powers and the duration of those regulations was legally limited to the duration of the emergency period itself (i.e. 3 months unless renewed).  [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "Yes - to the ICCPR and the ECHR [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Norway": {"code": "NO", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e3", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "10/01/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "20/03/2023"}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "No - Norway declared a public health emergency under the Health Preparedness Act 2000 but not under the Infection Control Act 1994, under which most public health interventions were made.", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "No", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No emergency declarations.", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "No [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes [Part I]. However, one formal constitutional amendment - not directly related to the pandemic. New electoral law, started being drafted in 2017. It includes rigorous emergency rules for elections. Rapporteurs argue that the political appetite was more pronounced due to the pandemic.", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "Yes. Infection control act that allowed Government to adopt secondary law that contained detailed regulations. It was amended over 300 times.", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "Yes - for the adoption of the Corona Act 2020 [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": 9, "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "Yes. Concerns over the Corona Act 2020 - public and political criticism of the draft bill led to significant reforms - but thereafter new bill was adopted unanimously. There were informal meetings between government and party opposition leaders. The parliament convened a group that consistend of five law professors, the judges association, the bar society, and the Norwegian Institute for Human Rights.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "Yes -  The Corona Act 2020 was fast-tracked and incited public debate, but was adopted unanimously by Parliament. The Government presented a draft to Parliament on 18 March 2020. Parliament negotiated with the Government for three days and invited a few institutions and legal scholars to assess the draft proposal. The hearings and the negotiations resulted in strengthened parliamentary scrutiny and judicial control as well as a more limited scope and time-frame for the Government’s powers. The Act passed the first reading on 21 March and the second on 24 March and was enacted on 27 March 2020. [Part II.B]", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "Yes - for the Corona Act 2020 [Part II.B]. Sunset provision was for 1 month, extended for another month.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "No - Elections held in September 2021 but not postponed, following legal advice by Eirik H. that to postpone elections would be unconstitutional [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "General elections, Norway (13 September)", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "No, but local restrictions on the mobility of citizens - it was advised (guidance) but not legally mandatory [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown of activies: there was no suspension but committees' activities were limited from 12 March 2020 for a month. There were also a reduction of MPs allowed to participate but minimum quorum requirements were respected [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A]. Supreme Court finally intervened in 2022. Courts were generally very slow to process cases - 6 months to access; 6 months to appeal; 6 months to have it decided by the Supreme Court.", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Yes, on an exceptional basis. The Norwegian Parliament engages in scrutiny of the Government’s performance chiefly through the normal parliamentary scrutiny system. This includes the weekly Question Time with Government ministers, written questions and interpellations addressed to ministers, debate on Covid-19-related bills presented by the Government, and through the functioning of various standing committees. All of these instruments have been actively used by opposition parties to scrutinize the Government’s response to Covid-19. [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "No. However, the Government can an on occasion does amend its own draft regulations. [Part III.A].", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "No. However, there are two kinds of regulations under the 1994 Act. In one category, if the regulation would derogate from primary law it had to be submitted to Parliament within 30 days of being made. In the other category of regulations, there is a general obligation to repeal the measure if it is considered no longer necessary but no specific sunset period.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Brazil": {"code": "BR", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e16", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "12/04/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "Yes. the Quarantine Act received several amendments in Congress and the imposition of the use of masks came from Congress against the wishes of the Executive [Part III.A]", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes - expires when the WHO declares the end of the PHEIC [Part II.B].", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "Dependent on the WHO", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes. A Public Health Emergency of National Importance (Emergência em Saúde Pública de Importância Nacional) (‘ESPIN’), was declared by the health secretary via Ordinance 188 of 3 February 2020, which implements Executive Decree 7.616 (17 November 2011) [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "Yes. Three days after Ordinance 188 of 3 February 2020 was issued, a more elaborate and detailed statute sailed through the Brazilian Congress in less than 48 hours: Federal Law 13.979 of 6 February 2020 (‘Quarantine Act’). [Part II.B]", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "Yes - for the Quarantine Act (48 hours) [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": 2, "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "No - As the speedy approval in Congress of the Quarantine Act testifies, there was little political opposition to it [Part II.B].", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "Yes - Important amendments to the Quarantine Act were added at the Chamber of Deputies (the lower house of Congress). ", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "Yes - for the Quarantine's Act [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Postponed (for mayors and local legislators - scheduled for 4 October 2020 and  postponed to 15 November 2020) [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Municipal elections, Brazil* (15 and 29 November 2020).", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "No [Part IV.A.1] - mobility restrictions were only imposed at state and municipal levels and varied widely across the country.", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Dependent on the jurisdiction that adopted it.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown in activities: recess was cancelled and the legislature was able to meet, either in virtual or semi-presential [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes - any measure can be challenged in court [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Yes - At the federal level, there was a reasonable degree of scrutiny through the debate and amendment of MPs and bills proposed by the federal executive and the independent initiation of bills by legislators which set the legal limits for the enactment of executive decrees and regulations. As we saw in Part II above, the Quarantine Act received several amendments in Congress and the imposition of the use of masks came from Congress against the wishes of the Executive [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Amendments possible (for the Quarantine Act [Part II.B] but not for provisional measures - Congress can confirm or reject, although it should be noted that it can fully or partially reject a measure [Part III.A]).", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes - for provisional measures [Part III.A].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Canada": {"code": "CA", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e15", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "11/04/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - not at the federal level [Part II.A], but at the provincial level [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes (at the state level) [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Depends on the state - in British Columbia, a state of emergency expire after 14 days [Part II.C].", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "NA [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes - not at the federal level [Part II.A] but at the provincial level [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No. Although the federal government did introduce new legislation to help respond to the crisis, this is not considered as a general Covid-19 responsive statute. For example, the federal government passed a series of bills, including Bill C-13, aimed at facilitating federal spending, easing the financial burden experienced by individuals and businesses by providing subsidies and payments for income lost due to Covid-19. [Part II.B]", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "Yes - The federal relief package received support from all political parties, however some members of the Conservative party pushed back against some sections of Bill C-13, arguing that specific provisions gave the executive too much power. Ultimately these controversial sections were removed or amended.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "Depends on the state.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Yes, postponed [IDEA]: 'By-elections in Victoria and Rossland, Canada (originally scheduled for 4 April 2020) moved to May 2021; referendum in Kamloops, Canada (originally scheduled for 4 April 2020) moved to May 2021; by-elections in Lytton, Canada (originally scheduled for 25 April 2020); municipal elections, New Brunswick, Canada (originally scheduled for 11 May 2020) moved to May 2021 or sooner'.", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "council election, Canada (26 March 2020);Saskatchewan provincial elections,  Canada (26 October 2020), Municipal by-election, Victoria, Canada* (12 December 2020), By-elections, Village of Lytton, British Colombia, Canada* (19 December 2020), Municipal elections, New Brunswick, Canada* (10 May 2021), General elections, Canada (20 September 2021)", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes - no 'strict lockdown' (except for Ontario long-term care homes) [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Mild interruption with important slowdown in activities: Parliament was adjourned between 13 March 2020 to 18 July 2020, but was recalled on 17 occasions in the meantime [Part III.B]. It was also scheduled to meet from 26 August 2020 to 31 September but on 18 August 2020 the Prime Minister prorogued Parliament until 23 September 2020. There were complaints regarding the limits imposed on parliamentary scrutiny.", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part II.C and III.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Yes - While Parliament has not played a significant oversight role, ‘the Senate and the House of Commons have variously authorized or mandated committees to provide ongoing oversight of the government’s response to Covid-19. [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Depends on the state - in Ontario, regulations expire after 14 days and Orders made under the Emergency Management and Civil Protection Act need to be extended for 30 days [Part II.C]. In BC, an order must specify the circumstances under which it expires [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "China": {"code": "CN", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e22", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "31/03/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "NA [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "NA [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No [Part II]", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "Yes - not officially but de facto [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "No (China does not conduct referendums, and direct elections are only conducted at the county and township levels. The new direct election is due in the first half of 2021, and at the time of writing, this election is scheduled to be conducted as originally planned) [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "None", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Mild interruption with important slowdown in activities: the annual meeting of the National People's Congress was postponed and later held in a shorter session from 22 to 28 May 2020. Standing committees could not really proceed with their work. Very little information regarding disruption and the encountered difficulties was available [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "No - theoretically some orders could be challenged in courts but it does depend on the legal source of the orders [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "No - Control measures were mostly issued by joint authorities of the Party and the government, leaving little room for supervision or approval by the legislature. This is so (as will be explained in Part II.C below) because the CPC is not subject to supervision by any state authorities [Part II.A].", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Ethiopia": {"code": "ET", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e20?rskey=uG9goG&result=94&prd=OXCON", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "26/07/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "Yes. The statutory law that is directly linked to the prevention of the spread of Covid-19 is the State of Emergency Proclamation No. 3/2020.50 This proclamation was fast-tracked in the sense that on 8 April 2020 the CoM, based on Article 93(1)(a) of the Constitution, declared a state of emergency. On 10 April 2020, the HPR endorsed the emergency proclamation in a single sitting day [Part II.B]", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 6, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "Yes", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "Yes - On 10 April 2020, the HPR endorsed the emergency proclamation in a single sitting day, and on 11 April the CoM issued Regulation 466/2020 which detailed the emergency measures. [Part III.B].", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": 1, "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "No - the HPR is dominated by the ruling party [Part III.A].", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "Yes - 5 months sunset provision for the declaration [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "Yes - possibility to suspend specific rights [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Postponed (the sixth general elections (elections to Parliament and state councils), which were scheduled for August 2020, were postponed after the NEBE declared that it would not be able to administer free and fair elections within the context of Covid-19. It became apparent elections could not be held before the expiry of the terms of Parliament and the state councils on 5 October 2020 when the Council of Ministers declared a state of emergency. This gave rise to the constitutional issues of whether elections could be postponed and who would govern at the federal and state level after the expiry of the terms of Parliament and the state councils. The HPR requested the intervention of the HoF in settling this constitutional matter, since the latter is the constitutional umpire of the federation. The HoF, as per the recommendation of the Commission Council of Constitutional of Inquiry (CCI) which assists the HoF in resolving constitutional issues, decided that the sixth general elections should be postponed until such time that the HPR, based on the advice of the MoH, decided that Covid-19 is no longer a public health threat. The elections would be held within a year after HPR so decides. In the meantime, Parliament,  and state councils, and federal and state executives would continue governing. It should be noted though that the Covid-19 was not the sole reason for the postponement of the elections. The political crisis that began after the 2015 elections which, until even today, continues in one form or another was perhaps the key factor for the postponement of the elections. Secession of the Tigray state. On 29 December 2020, the NEBE announced that the elections would be held on 5 June 2021) [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Ethiopia* (General elections, 21 June 2021).", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "No - no general lockdown or mobility measures imposed nationwide [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown in activities: Parliament continued to function more or less routinely [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not possible [Part III.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "No - there is no possibility for courts to interpret the Constitution nor to review the legality of a state of emergency [Part III.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "No amendment possible (for declaration of emergency and content of the measures) [Part II.C].", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "Yes de facto [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Germany": {"code": "DE", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e2", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "15/12/2020"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - 'epidemic emergency of national concern' [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "Yes", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes [Part III.A].", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 12, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes but crucial legal questions were raised [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No - but 'interference' with fundamental rights [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Yes - in 2020, only elections at local level had to be held during the pandemic. Whereas the first ballot of the local elections in Bavaria in mid-March 2020 was not decisively affected by the beginning spread of Covid-19 at that time, the second ballot on 29 March 2020, though not postponed, was exclusively organized as a postal vote with the respective documents being sent automatically to all eligible voters. In North Rhine-Westphalia, the parliament enacted a law facilitating the local elections, eg by extending deadlines for applications of candidates, that finally took place as planned in September 2020) [prt III.D]. IDEA: 'Local elections in Hessen and Saxony, Germany (originally scheduled for April–October 2020) moved (Hessen) to 14 March 2021'.", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "local elections in Bavaria, Germany (first round 16 March 2020 and second round 29 March 2020); Local elections, North-Rhine Westphalia, Germany (13 September 2020), State and local elections, Saxony and Brandenburg, Germany (27 September 2020), State elections, Rheinland-Pfalz, Germany (14 March 2021), State elections, Baden-Wurttemberg, Germany (14 March 2021), Saxon-Anhalt state elections, Germany (6 June 2021), Federal elections, Germany (26 September 2021)", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes (Länder implemented) [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Mild interruption with important slowdown in activities: parliamentary groups were reduced, but the scheduled recess in the summer was neither extended nor postponed [Part III.B]. Parliament's work has not been interrupted irregularly, and committees were able to meet and vote virtually (not the plenary).", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes, all measures are subject to scrutiny by courts [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Yes - In addition to these amendments of the Infection Protection Act 2000, the Bundestag passed numerous bills in order to cope with the crisis in all fields of law. For instance, two so-called ‘Social Security Bundles’ amended a series of laws in the field of social legislation. Of great importance was also the adoption of two supplementary budget acts by the Bundestag,40 considerably expanding financial discretion at the federal level [Part II.B]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Yes, for the amendments on previously exisiting statutes [Part III.A].", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Ireland": {"code": "IE", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e19", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "30/12/2020"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes, Constitutional Covid-related Emergency Regulations were issued under the Basic Law: The Government. However, a state of emergency was not specially declared in the context of the pandemic, but had instead been in existence (and annually renewed) since the foundation of the modern state of Israel in 1948. Furthermore, a number of statutory emergencies were declared ", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "No - the authors note that the use of 'emergency' in a statute does not have any formal legal consequences [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "Constitutional Covid-related Emergency Regulations were issued under the Basic Law: The Government. However, a state of emergency was not specially declared in the context of the pandemic, but had instead been in existence (and annually renewed) since the foundation of the modern state of Israel in 1948.", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes, a number of statutory emergencies were declared  [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "Yes", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "Yes - 'expedited process' - the President disapplied the usual five-day waiting period before signing the acts into law [Part II.B] (the Health (Preservation and Protection and other Emergency Measures in the Public Interest) Act 2020 and the Emergency Measures in the Public Interest (Covid-19) Act 2020).", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": 1, "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "No - the opposition supported amendments to pre-existing acts or new acts [Part II.B] but requested increased information and transparency [Part III.B].", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B and C].", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "No - General election took place in February 2020. An indirect election for Seanad Éireann took place after the 2020 Irish general election, with postal ballots due on 30 and 31 March 2020. Seanad elections usually take place by postal ballot and this was not a departure from the usual electoral procedure. The Seanad was unable to sit formally until the appointment by the incoming Taoiseach of his 11 nominees on 27 June 2020) [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Seanad general election (partially indirect), Ireland (30-31 March 2020)", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Yes (27 March 2020 to 12 April 2020, then extended) [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Mild interruption with important slowdown in activities: there were no ordinary committee meetings between January and October 2020  but the special Covid-19 committee met for 29 days. The Dail sat at a reduced capacity, and the House of Representatives could not pass primary legislation from 29 March 2020 to 27 June 2020 because of the extended period of time during which the Seanad was not sitting [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B and C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Yes - while the constitution requires a degree of ex ante ‘oversight’, there is also a practice of requiring certain regulations or decrees to be placed before the Oireachtas. Given its primacy, it is also, in principle, open to the Oireachtas to repeal subordinate legislation at any time [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes, in the SI [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Mexico": {"code": "MX", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e14?utm_campaign=oupac-campaign:1403734642106728324&utm_source=Twitter&utm_medium=social&utm_content=post:1413890015695870440&utm_term=OUP%20Law", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "15/02/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - 'public health emergency' [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No. The legislature has no say in the declaration of emergency for the purposes of Article 73 XVI of the Constitution or its duration, ie whether and when it should be terminated [Part III.A]", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "No [Part III.A].", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "Yes - while a public health emergency declaration was published by the General Health Council on 30 March 2020, it is not a state of exception foreseen by Article 29 of the Constitution, which so far has not been declared. [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Postponed (two local elections were postponed until proper measures to guarantee the safety of voters amidst the pandemic were implemented—the states of Coahuila and Hidalgo suspended local legislative elections and municipal elections, respectively) [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Local elections in Coahuila, Mexico* (18 October 2020), Legislative elections, Mexico (6 June 2021), Referendum, Mexico (1 August 2021).", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "No - recommendation thereof but not binding. And recommendations only at the state level [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Mild interruption and important slowdown in activities: there was a suspension of plenum activities [Part III.B] but online sessions were held in commissions. The ordinary period was suspended prematurely on 30 April 2020, and activities resumed in an hybrid format on 14 September 2020.", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No [Part III.C].", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes - all acts maybe challenged in courts [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "No - The legislature may not review the executive’s emergency declaration under Article 73 XVI of the Constitution, nor the measures mandated under its purview, they may scrutinise the acts of public officials during hearings [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Netherlands": {"code": "NL", "url": "", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "Forthcoming"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - not at the federal level, but at the state level.", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "Yes", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "Yes - New act was approved within 3 months, which is exceptional in the Dutch legislative process [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "Less than 3 months", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "Yes. Pre-enactment: opposed by both left and right-wing parties in the Second Chamber- changes made before enactment. Post- enactment: critically commented on by several civil society organizations.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "Yes, the new statute expires after three months [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No but restrictions [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "No [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "House of Representatives elections, Netherlands (17-19 March 2021)", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "No, were guidance (but curfew) [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown in activities - no meetings officially suspended, whether in plenary sessions or committee meetings, but the upper house of Parliament did de facto not meet between 17 March 2020 and April 2020 [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No - but important role of the Dutch Council of State which advises the Government and the Parliament on new legislation and policy [Part III.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes - but not over declarations of state of emergency [Part III.C] because it is a declared by means of a royal decree. But individual measures can be challenged in court [Part IV.A].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "New Zealand": {"code": "NZ", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e4", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "15/12/2020"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - state of national emergency + epidemic notice [Part II.A]. Also transition period.", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "Yes. The declaration of the state of emergency and issue of an epidemic notice were, as required, subsequently notified to Parliament and subject to debate, although Parliament has no role in approving these emergency declarations [Part II.B]", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B]. A state of national emergency was declared on 25 March 2020 under the Civil Defence Emergency Management Act 2002 and renewed six times, until finally expiring on 13 May 2020", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 1, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes - under health and civil defence legislation [Part II.A and B]. ", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "Yes", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "Yes - for the adoption of the Covid-19 Public Health Response Act 2020 [Part II.B] (2 days) and other legislation.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": 2, "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "Yes. Opposition to the bill but the Government immediately appointed a select committee in response to concerns raised.\n", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "Yes - The Opposition—the group of political parties and MPs not in government—opposed the bill, raising process, design, civil liberties, and enforcement concerns. [Part II.B]", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "Yes - 90 days [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Postponed - The general election was originally scheduled for 19 September 2020 but was briefly delayed after a small regional outbreak of the virus. As Parliament had not been formally dissolved (although was set to be the day after the outbreak emerged), the Prime Minister retained exclusive power to advise the Governor-General on dissolution of Parliament and specification of polling day, subject to the maximum term of Parliament. After consulting other political parties—most of which, including coalition and support parties, favoured a delay—and electoral officials, the Prime Minister deferred the election for four weeks until 17 October 2020. Parliament was dissolved for the general election on 6 September 2020, sitting for three weeks further than anticipated) [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "General Election and Referendum New Zealand* (17 October 2020)", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Mild interruption with important slowdown in activities - after an initial suspension from 25 March to 28 April 2020, sessions resumed [Part III.B]. Select committees continued to perform their usual functions during the alert level 3 and 4 lockdown. Usual operation of Parliament resumed in mid-May 2020, as the country moved to alert level 2 on 14 May 2020.", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Yes. The Regulations Review Committee scrutinised health and Covid-19 orders. [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Pakistan": {"code": "PK", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e25", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "04/04/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - at the federal level, there was no official declaration but the executive exercised wide powers de facto; declarations of emergency at the states' level [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes - at the state level [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A).", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes - not at the federal but state level [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "Yes", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "Yes - A standing committee’s report had been sought by the Assembly, but the enactment was fast-tracked in view of the committee’s failure to present its report within the specified period of two months [Part II.B]", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": 17, "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "Yes - the opposition criticised the suspension of Parliament and boycotted the parliamentary special committee on Covid-19 [Part III.B].", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "No - Although the ordinances promulgated in the Punjab and Sindh were subsequently adopted as statutes by their respective legislatures, there were no substantive amendments brought about in their contents during the enactment process [Part III.A]", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "No. There is neither any sunset clause in the Act, nor is the nature of the powers temporary in any sense other than being exercisable during the subsistence of a (declared) public health emergency [Part II.B]", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Postponed (since the general elections are not due until 2023, there was no major election activity expected at the time of the outbreak. However, by-elections were due to fill some vacant seats in the National and Provincial Assemblies. Despite such by-elections being required to be held within 60 days (Article 224(4) of the Constitution), the ECP had to postpone them because of the pandemic. Ultimately the ECP, in line with the NCOC’s recommendations, deferred by-elections for 8 constituencies) [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Gilgit-Baltistan assembly elections, Pakistan* (15 November 2020), By-elections Sindh and Balochistan Assembly, Pakistan*, (16 February 2021).", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes - only at the provincial level [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Yes - 15 days for the Sindh Government", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Severe interruption + suspension of activities - Parliament's session was cut short by a week on 13 March 2020 and it is only after a suspension of two months that the Parliament resumed its activities on 11 May 2020. This gap was by far the longest between two sessions of the National Assembly under the tenure of the current government [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part III.A].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "No.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes - ordinances (120 days) [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Portugal": {"code": "PT", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e23?rskey=AkInlr&result=19&prd=OCC19", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "20/04/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A and C].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "Yes - The President of the Republic has the power to declare the state of emergency, but only after consulting the Government and seeking parliamentary authorization.", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes (15 days) [Part II.A].", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 1, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "Yes (state of emergency) [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes (state of alert and calamity) [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No, but the implementation of the state of emergency in the regions has been problematic [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No - In the fight against the pandemic, the Government relied mainly on legislation that predated the pandemic for the primary public health measures [Part II.B]", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No (but restrictions) [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "No [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Presidential elections, Portugal (24 January 2021), Local Elections, Portugal (26 September 2021), Parliamentary election, Portugal (30 January 2022) ", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes - A second set of measures was in force between 18 March and 2 May 2020, during the first state of emergency and its renewals stay-at-home measures were in place but not curfews. [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Yes", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Mild interruption with slowdown in activities (the authors indicate that plenary and parliamentary committees meetings were reduced to when they were necessary and this curtailed the parliamentary oversight) [Part III.A].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No (the authors mention that a Constitutional Court review of the state of emergency is possible but don't specify whether it is ex ante) [Part II.C].", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Yes, possibility to amend the state of emergency [Part II.A].", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes (for Decree-Laws, sunset provisions range from 6 months to one year) [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Russia": {"code": "RU", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e27?rskey=wh1OaL&result=283&prd=OXCON", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "01/08/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - 'state of high alert' [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "Not mentioned. Also, emergencies declared at the federation unit level (85 declarations)", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "No [Part III.A].", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No - The Constitution recognizes two forms of exceptional regimes in response to extraordinary situations: martial law (Article 87) and state of emergency (Article 88), neither of which has been utilized in Russia in response to the Covid-19 pandemic. [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes, at the federation units level - Despite no obvious formal coordination, in the period between 27 January and 20 March 2020 all 85 federated units reacted to the pandemic in a similar way by enacting 85 declarations of the state of high alert [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes - but constitutional reforms benefitted from the lockdown [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No - he Russian legislator did not enact a new general law with emergency powers to respond to Covid-19. Instead, the legal reaction to the spread of the virus was primarily based on two pre-pandemic federal laws: the aforementioned 1994 Federal Law on Protection of the Population and Territories against Natural and Man-Induced Disasters (Federal Law No 68-FZ) and the 1999 Federal Law on the Sanitary and Epidemiological Wellbeing of the Population (Federal Law No 52-FZ) [Part II.B]", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "Yes - the RCC has decided to allow the Government to depart from stringent standards of protection of constitutional rights [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Postponed (the popular vote on constitutional amendments initially scheduled for 22 April 2020, was postponed due the difficult epidemiological situation. Eventually, the plebiscite was organized in the last week of June 2020 (ended 1 July 2020) in a peculiar procedure regulated ad hoc by the Central Election Commission of Russia. The legal framework that deviated from the regular electoral procedure prescribed by federal law raised serious concerns of scholars, civil activists, and observers. Elections scheduled for the ‘unified voting day’ (13 September 2020) proceeded without suspension. Elections were held in 83 subjects of the Russian Federation, around 9,000 thousand public officials of federal, regional, and local levels were elected. However, in May and July 2020, federal electoral legislation was subjected to major modifications, explained, to some extent, by high epidemiological risks) [Part III.D]. IDEA: 'The Central Election Commission of Russia took the decision (3 April 2020) to postpone all elections initially scheduled in the period 5 April–23 June, covering about 94 electoral processes at local and regional levels'.", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Constitutional nation-wide referendum, Russia* (1 July 2020); Local elections, Russia, some local elections were held after being postponed in April and May 2020* (13 September 2020), Legislative elections, Russia (17-19 September 2021).", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes, at the local level - The Decree of the Mayor of 29 March 2020 imposed the stay-at-home obligation on all residents of Moscow. The general stay-at-home order lasted from 30 March until 8 June 2020. [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Mild interruption with important slowdown of activities - Parliament's work has been affected but not interrupted, and activities continued even at the height of the pandemic. Activities shifted online [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part II.C; Part III.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "No - On the level of federated units, the role of legislatures in supervising the executive is also insignificant. The mechanisms of oversight are similar to the ones that exist on the federal level—the annual report of the highest official (governor, mayor, or head of the federated unit) before the regional parliament, participation of executive authorities in the parliamentary sessions, and a parliamentary vote of no-confidence. Regional parliaments do not have the power to repeal regulations adopted by the executive, but may only suggest that the cabinet or the governor amend their acts, or appeal to the court with a request to review executive regulations [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "No [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Serbia": {"code": "RS", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e7", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "16/12/2020"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - state of emergency [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes but the Government also relied on two acts prior to and after the state of emergency to adopt specific measures [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "Yes -The Constitution authorises the National Assembly to make a declaration ‘when the survival of the state or its citizens is threatened by a public danger.’ On such an occasion, the National Assembly convenes without any special call for assembly and may not be dissmissed. This decision can be effective for 90 days, and can be extended for another 90 days. When the National Assembly is not in a position to convene, the decision is adopted by the President, together with the Speaker and the Prime Minister, as was the case in 2020. However, even then, the Assembly must approve the state of emergency as soon as possible. [Part II.A]", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "Yes - Relying on Article 200 of the Constition, Serbia declared a state of emergency on 15 March 2020, which was then lifted on 6 May 2020. [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes but all decisions were de facto in the hands of the executive [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No - There was no new general law introduced to provide emergency powers to respond to Covid-19. The legal framework for dealing with Covid-19 in Serbia is instead based on two distinct foundations. [Part II.B]", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "Yes - to the extent that is necessary [Prart II.C] but there is a list of rights that cannot be derogated from [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Postponed (the parliamentary, provincial, and municipal elections in Serbia were initially scheduled for 26 April 2020. On 15 March 2020 the decision was taken to suspend them. The state of emergency was lifted on 6 May 2020, along with several precautionary measures. Therefore, on 10 May 2020, the President of the Republic adopted the Decision that elections would be held on 21 June 2020, and on the following day the Republic Election Commission adopted an Order on continuation of all election activities) [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Parliamentary, provincial and local elections*, Serbia (21 June 2020), Referendum, Serbia (16 January 2022).", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes - On 15 March 2020, the state of emergency and lockdown in Serbia were announced by the President on television and stipulated in a Decree on measures during a state of emergency. [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Yes - The Decree would be in force until 6 May 2020.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Severe interruption with severe suspension in activities - the National Assembly was almost inactive from March to October 2020 and convened only 6 weeks after the declaration of the state of emergency [Part III.B]. All operations were suspended and only resumed from 29 April 2020 (until 3 June 2020). It has also been very difficult for MPs to participate in debates and parliamentary committees could not continue to meet.", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes - all legal acts taken by the executive are subect to constitutional scrutiny [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "No - s the National Assembly did not meet for 44 days (from 16 March to 28 April 2020) and was dissolved on 3 June 2020, it was unable to perform its oversight functions, which are traditionally exercised through the work of committees, (especially the Health and Family Committee), public hearings, and parliamentary questions [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Singapore": {"code": "SG", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e30", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "26/04/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "NA [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "NA [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "Yes - Parliament passed the Covid-19 (Temporary Measures) Act (‘CTMA’), which, having been expedited under a Certificate of Urgency signed by the President [Part II.B]", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "Yes, for the CTMA - was introduced, debated, and passed on the same day (7 April 2020) [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": 1, "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "No - The enactment of the CTMA did not attract any dissent from the (then) only opposition party in Parliament [Part II.B].", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "Not mentioned", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "Yes - Initially, CTMA provided that its provisions granting these powers would remain in force until 7 April 2021. By an amendment taking effect on 1 March 2021 and voted for unanimously in Parliament, these powers are now in force until the end of 8 April 2022 [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "The general election was called in advance [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Parliamentary elections, Singapore (10 July 2020); ", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes - During the ‘circuit breaker’ period from 7 April to 1 June 2020, the Control Order Regulations prohibited every individual from leaving their ordinary place of residence, subject to certain exceptions. [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Yes - During the ‘circuit breaker’ period from 7 April to 1 June 2020, the Control Order Regulations prohibited every individual from leaving their ordinary place of residence, subject to certain exceptions. [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown: Parliament has continued to sit as usual [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes, in principle eve though the authors say that any constitutional challenge owuld be limited [Part III.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Yes - First, Parliament retains oversight of all control orders. Control orders and their amendments come into force upon publication in the government Gazette by the Minister. However, all published control orders and amendments must be presented to Parliament ‘as soon as possible after publication in the Gazette’. Parliament may thus annul any control order, amendment, or any part thereof by passing a resolution, albeit without affecting anything previously done under that control order or part thereof [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Yes", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes for regulations issued under the CTMA, which will cease to be valid when the relevant provisions will expire, but not for the regulations issued under the Infectious Diseases Act.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "South Africa": {"code": "ZA", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e6", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "18/12/2020"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A and B].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes [Part II.C].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes - The initial state of disaster lapsed on 15 June 2020. [Part II.B].", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 3, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes - national state of disaster [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No - There was no new general law introduced to provide emergency powers in response to Covid-19 [Part II.B].", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No, only limitations are allowed and must comply with constitutional requirements [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Postponed (The Independent Electoral Commission (IEC) lodged an urgent application with the Electoral Court requesting the postponement of municipal by-elections and associated activities such as voter registration that were originally scheduled for March, April, and May 2020. On 19 March 2020, the Electoral court granted the urgent application and postponed by-elections. The court additionally ruled that the by-elections could be held beyond the 90-day legislated period for the filling of councillor vacancies but not beyond 120 days from the date of the order. However, the prolonged state of national disaster required the court to further postpone the by-elections twice and to revise the electoral timetable for the by-elections accordingly. After consultations with the Minister of Cooperative Governance and Traditional Affairs and a special National Party Liaison Committee representing political parties, the IEC resolved ‘to clear the backlog of all outstanding by-elections on 11 November 2020’. On that date, by-elections took place in 96 wards in 56 municipalities countrywide) [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "By-elections, South Africa* (11 November 2020), Local elections, South Africa (1 November 2021).", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes - Under what was popularly referred to as a ‘hard lockdown’, from 26 March to 31 April 2020, all persons throughout the country were fully confined to their places of residence, except for providing or obtaining essential services or goods, collecting a social grant, seeking emergency medical treatment, or obtaining chronic medication [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Yes - Under what was popularly referred to as a ‘hard lockdown’, from 26 March to 31 April 2020, all persons throughout the country were fully confined to their places of residence, except for providing or obtaining essential services or goods, collecting a social grant, seeking emergency medical treatment, or obtaining chronic medication [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown: the pandemic coincided with the Easter recess; Parliament resumed its activities on 13 April 2020 and all scheduled leave was cancelled. The sessions were virtual at first and then hybrid [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No (not for the pre-declaration).", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes, all executive decisions are subject to judicial review for constitutional compliance. Controversy over the creation of the NCCC but upheld by courts [Part III.A].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Yes - regulations made by the Minister in terms of the Act must be referred to the National Council of Provinces, whose approval would be required in order for the regulation to prevail over conflicting provincial legislation under section 146(6) of the 1996 Constitutio [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes - regulations promulgated in terms of the Disaster Management Act 2002 remain in force until repealed, or until the state of disaster lapses [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "South Korea": {"code": "KR", "url": "", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "Forthcoming"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No - As the authority of issuing a crisis alert belongs to the executive body, the National Assembly has not played a role in this regard [Part II.B].", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "No [Part III.C].", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes - the Government issued a crisis alert under the Framework Act on the Management of Disasters and Safety (article 38) [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No - The National Assembly has not adopted new legislation for the purpose of allocating the power of responding to Covid-19 among different government bodies [Part II.B].", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No but restrictions [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "No [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "parliamentary elections in South Korea (15 April 2020).", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "No [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown [Part III.B]: no closure, occasions when committee meetings or seminars were cancelled or postponed due to the infection of a news reporter or a self-quarantine of one of the Assembly members.", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part III.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "No - The legislature in South Korea (either the National Assembly or the local legislature) does not assume a role of ongoing oversight over government decrees or executive rule-making [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "No [Part III.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Spain": {"code": "ES", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e10?rskey=RwERE0&result=1&prd=OXCON", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "12/01/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes, nationwide 'state of alarm' for the first wave of the pandemic. Then local state of alarm in 3 municipalities of Madrid against will of local leaders during second wave. There was another nationwide state of alarm [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No. Congress’s powers are exclusive when it comes to the authorization of an extension of a state of alarm beyond the period of the initial declaration, when it can also set the effects and scope of the declaration, therefore not being restricted to simply casting a yes or no vote [Part II.A].", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes - During the first wave of the pandemic, the Spanish Government declared a nationwide state of alarm for a total period of three months, from 14 March until 21 June 2020. It declared it for an initial period of 15 days, and subsequently extended every fortnight, six times, with the approval of the Congress.[Part II.A].", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 1, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes but tensions [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No - No new general law was introduced providing emergency powers to respond to Covid-19. However, the general framework described above has been subject to a relevant amendment through Law 3/2020, an ordinary Act of Parliament which modified several provisions of the Act on Contentious-Administrative Courts [Part II.B].", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No (Art. 55[1] Constitution) - debate regarding whether public health measures were restrictions or suspensions of fundamental rights [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Postponed - The pandemic provoked the postponement of the autonomic elections in Galicia and the Basque Country which had been initially scheduled for 5 April 2020 but took place on 12 July 2020 [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Regional elections in Euskadi/Basque and Galicia, Spain* (12 July 2020); Catalonia regional elections, Spain (14 February 2020)", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes - During the first state of alarm (14 March to 21 June 2020), a general stay-at-home order was imposed by the Spanish Government nationwide through Royal Decree 463/2020. Persons could leave their home only if they had a ‘reasonable excuse’, such as the need to provide care or assistance, to travel for the purposes of work, or to access critical public services (Article 7) [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Yes.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Mild interruption with important slowdown in activities - Parliament was able to meet and perform its functions although there were disruptions in the first months of the pandemic. On 12 March 2020, Parliament was suspended for 15 days, except for a scheduled appearance of the Minister of Health before the Congress’ Committee for Health and for plenary sessions devoted to validation of royal decree-laws and extensions of the state of alarm. On 21 April, sessions resumed. After the initial period of disruption, parliamentary committees began to meet and to conduct their business without significant alterations. There have been complaints by opposition parties regarding the disproportionate political constraints imposed on parliamentary scrutiny during the pandemic [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes - measures adopted under the state of alarm can be scrutinised by the judiciary [Part II.A and C] but only the SCC can review the declaration of the state of alarm.", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "No - public health regulations, directions, and guidance are not subject to a formal procedure of confirmation/rejection by Parliament. However, both the Congress of Deputies and Senate control all actions of Government in weekly control sessions, mainly through questions and interpellations, requests for information, and parliamentary commissions of investigation [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Amendment possible (Congress shall be informed of the declaration of the state of alarm and must meet immediately for this purpose. Congress’s powers are exclusive when it comes to the authorization of an extension of a state of alarm beyond the period of the initial declaration, when it can also set the effects and scope of the declaration, therefore not being restricted to simply casting a yes or no vote) [Part II.A]. But As regards royal decree-laws, Congress decides whether they should be confirmed through a yes or no vote which does not allow for amendments [Part III.A].", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Varies - regulations usually have no sunset clauses, except for those adopted on the basis of the state of alarm - usually applicable until the end of the emergency declaration [Part II.C]. In some cases, however, royal decree-laws and regulations adopted to fight the crisis expressly set out that some of their provisions shall cease to have effect after a specific date.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Sweden": {"code": "SE", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e12", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "14/01/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "No [Part II.A]. It was the designation of Covid-19 as dangerous to public health enabled the applicability of extraordinary measures. In addition, a specific Covid-19 Act was passed (of temporary nature) [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "NA [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "NA [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "Yes - a new general law, the Covid-19 Act entered into force on the 10 January 2021. This Act has a temporary nature, expiring at the end of September 2021, and allows for enactment of specific pandemic related delegated decrees [Part II.B].", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "No. It is possible that legislation has been prioritized or fast-tracked and tabled for approval to the detriment of other less time sensitive matters, however this could not be confirmed officially [Part II.C]", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "No - no significant complaints [Part III.B].", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "Yes - for the Covid-19 Act [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No, only very few restrictions on fundamental rights [Part II.A] and no suspension of fundamental rights possible [Part IV.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "No (no elections or referendums were scheduled to take place and therefore there was no disruption caused) [Part III.D]. IDEA: 'Local referendum, Malung-Sälen, Sweden​ (originally scheduled for 17 May 2020) moved to 27 September 2020'.", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Local referendum, Malung-Sälen, Sweden* (27 September 2020), Sametinget, Sweden(16 May 2021).", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "No [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown: Parliament continued its work, but a reduced number of members could participate; committees continued to meet [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes - in principle possible [Part II.C; Part III.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes - except for some decrees that are not limited in time [Part II.C]", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Taiwan": {"code": "TW", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e18", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "22/04/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "No [Part II.A]. The Executive Yuan relied on pre-pandemic statutes, such as the CDC Act. A Covid-19 Special Act was also passed [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "NA [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "NA [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "Yes - After 20 legislators proposed the Covid-19 Special Act on 19 February 2020, it only took 6 days before it was passed and promulgated [Part II.B]", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "Yes - for the adoption of the Covid-19 Special Act (6 days) [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": 6, "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "No - the Democratic Party had just won elections by a landslide, so this, in addition to the public support for the measures, did potentially discourage legislators from further scrutiny [Part III.B].", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "Not mentioned. It says that the act had amendments, but not necessarily proposed/secured by the opposition [Part II.B]", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "Yes - for the Covid-19 Special Act [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "No (all elections in Taiwan were carried out on schedule this year. After the CECC was set up in response to the pandemic on 20 January 2020, there have been more than ten elections or by-elections and one recall so far, ranging from a town mayor to the mayor of Kaohsiung, a major city in Taiwan) [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "local by-elections in Taiwan (22 February 2020);", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "No [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown: the legislature and the committees operated normally during the pandemic [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes, it is possible [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Yes - possibility for the Legislative Yuan to ask the Executive Yuan to alter a policy [Part III.A].", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No, not from HR treaties (but from the GATT [Part II.A]).", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Thailand": {"code": "TH", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e29?rskey=CP7rdv&result=27&prd=OCC19", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "20/09/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - 'state of emergency' [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No [Part II..A]", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes - In general, an emergency situation automatically expires within 90 days from the date of its issuance. However, the PM may call for its extension for an additional 90 days simply with the approval of their cabinet. The declaration authorizes the PM to consolidate power from a number of acts within themselves. He may bypass any laws and regulations with impunity. Prayuth declared a three-month state of emergency nationwide on 26 March 2020. As of August 2021, the Cabinet has extended the declaration indefinitely with no end in sight. [Part II.A].", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 3, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes - (and also through the 2005 Decree) [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No - No new Act of Parliament has been promulgated in response specifically to Covid-19 [Part II.B]", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "No (no election was suspended. The last general election was in March 2019, so there would not be any no general election until 2023 anyhow. Since Covid-19 struck, the Election Commission has held two by-elections and two nation-wide local elections, all of which were on schedule) [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Provincial elections, Thailand (20 December 2020)", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "No - or limited to an encouragement for certain categories of the population with a high risk of infection - Regulation no. 1 did not forbid citizen mobility, it simply encouraged certain categories of individuals who were at high risk if infected to stay home [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown in activities - the parliamentary session continued with minimal interruption. It closed prematurely in April 2020 but resumed as planned on 22 May 2020. There was a 2-day suspension on 24-25 December 2020 but committees could meet. The premature closure of Parliament was criticised by the opposition [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "No, not possible (ouster clause that prevents regulations from being reviewed by the Administrative Court) [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "No - The Parliament does not have an ongoing oversight role over decree- or rule-making powers of the Cabinet [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Turkey": {"code": "TR", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e33?rskey=uODCcv&result=30&prd=OCC19", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "08/07/2020"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "No [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "NA [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "NA - but used specific laws to impose specific measures despite the absence of declaration [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No, but the authors mention that confusion arose due to the fact that no state of emergency was declared but fundamental rights were restricted [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No - The GNAT has approved no new general law to provide a legal basis for the restrictions and measures imposed to address the pandemic [Part II.B]", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "No national elections were postponed, but municipal elections were postponed [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "None", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "No general stay at home orders - some limited to certain age categories, and multiple curfews [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Mild interruption with mild slowdown (cf. prorogations and periods of recesses but the authors highlight that this is not out of the ordinary) [Part III.A).", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "United Kingdom": {"code": "GB", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e17", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "08/10/2020"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "No - but an 'emergency procedure' under the 1984 Act [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "No - but an 'emergency procedure' under the 1984 Act [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No emergency declarations.", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "NA [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "NA - but an 'emergency procedure' under the 1984 Act [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes but exacerbated problems [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "Yes", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "Yes - Though it had its first reading (published, but without debate) on 19 March 2020, it had three sitting days of parliamentary scrutiny (23–25 March 2020), only one of which was in the House of Commons. [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": 3, "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "Yes - Minor criticism relating mostly to the short timeframe of the passage and associated constrained scrutiny.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "There is parliamentary scrutiny of public health regulations, as noted above, but it has been truncated and exacerbates long-recognised difficulties with the general process. Scrutiny permits approval or rejection, but not amendment [Part III.A]", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "Yes - for the Coronavirus Act 2020 and the Scotland Coronavirus Act [Part II.B].", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Yes, postponed - The Electoral Commission, an independent body, wrote to the UK Government on 10 March 2020 asking that local and other elections in England and Wales be suspended on health grounds for both members of the general public and for polling station staff. Section 60 of the Coronavirus Act 2020 postpones ‘7 May Elections’ (ie local government elections, Mayor of London and London Assembly elections, elected mayors of local and combined authorities, and police and crime commissioners) to the same or near date the following year. It ultimately postponed local elections due for 118 councils, mayoral and some assembly elections in the Greater London Assembly, and a variety of other elections. Some local referendums and council by-elections were also cancelled. The 2020 Act also deals with by-elections to various assemblies (section 61), and postpones elections under the Recall of MPs Act 2015 (section 62). The Government confirmed in February 2021 that scheduled local government elections in May 2021 would be proceeding, with advice to use postal and proxy voting where possible. The 2020 Act did not affect scheduled elections to the Scottish Parliament and the Welsh Parliament due on 6 May 2021, which are due to go ahead as planned) [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Local, Mayoral* and Parliamentary elections, United Kingdom (6 May 2021),.", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Yes (12 months) [Part II.C].", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown in activities - recess was one to 2 weeks longer than usual [Part III.B]. The Government moved a resolution on 2 June 2020 to end the use of remote-voting and required any MPs to participate within the parliamentary estate. That ended the use of hybrid proceedings, though within 10 days the Government permitted the re-introduction of hybrid proceedings for scrutiny proceedings (ie oral questions and ministerial statements) but not substantive proceedings (eg legislative scrutiny): this has been criticised. The House of Lords, where the Government’s party holds no majority, quickly made provision for hybrid proceedings and online voting (through ‘PeerHub’), the latter of which commenced on 15 June 2020. All of its committees have met online after Parliament began sitting on 21 April 2020. Both Houses performed their core functions.", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part III.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "There is parliamentary scrutiny of public health regulations, as noted above, but it has been truncated and exacerbates long-recognised difficulties with the general process. Scrutiny permits approval or rejection, but not amendment [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "No amendment possible [Part III.C].", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes - in practice, a wide variety of sunset periods were used in health regulations and many are listed in early correspondence between the Government and the House of Lords Secondary Legislation Scrutiny Committee [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "United States": {"code": "US", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e24", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "01/10/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B] (HHS Secretary declared federal emergency + at the state level).", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No - Section 319 (also known as Section 247d, following codification) authorizes the HHS Secretary—the equivalent to a national minister of health—to determine that a public health emergency exists. This determination, which does not require legislative approval, triggers emergency powers delegated by Congress in advance [Part II.B]", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes [Part III.A]; at the state level, varies. Not mentioned at the federal level.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No changes but tested the limits of constitutional arrangements [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No - The vast majority of public health directives to respond to Covid-19 in the US have been adopted via executive declarations and orders that rely on pre-pandemic statutory provisions, rather than via new legislation or rulemaking [Part II.B]", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "Yes.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Postponed in some states (2020 was a major election year in the United States, including the election of the President, the entire House, a third of the Senate, and thousands of state and local races. State officials have authority over elections, including elections for federal candidates and officials. In March 2020, primary elections were scheduled to take place in states across the country. Governors issued executive orders postponing some elections and permitting voting by mail in others) [Part III.D]. [IDEA]: 'Primary elections across the USA; several local elections around the country (originally scheduled for March–May 2020) moved to May-August 2020.'", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Local, state and national elections", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes, in most states [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown: the US Congress continued to meet in person [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A and C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Not at the federal level - At the federal level, Congress has not acted during the pandemic to limit the authority of the President, the HHS Secretary, or the CDC Director. In several states, however, legislatures have sought to reverse the decisions of governors and health officials, including by filing court challenge [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "No (only comments for New York for instance)", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Colombia": {"code": "CO", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e34", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "01/03/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - 'state of exception', twice [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes[Part II.B].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "Yes - During both states of exception that followed the WHO Covid-19 pandemic declaration, the Congress of Colombia has indeed exercised supervisory powers. To study the convenience and opportunity of the emergency declarations and the measures taken to overcome the crisis, each chamber of the Congress (Senate and the House of Representatives) appointed one ‘special commission’ to scrutinize the opportunity and convenience of each of the emergency declarations {Part III.A]", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes - [Part II.A]", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 2, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "Yes [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes - statutory state of health emergency [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No - Congress did not need to pass any general law to provide powers in order to address the Covid-19 crisis [Part II.B].", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "No, the pandemic has not caused any major disruptions to national or regional elections, nor to referendums since none were scheduled to take place during 2020 or 2021 [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "None", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes - The national Government has ordered several national mobility restriction measures during the aislamiento preventivo obligatorio (preventive mandatory isolation) period. These measures were in effect across the country from 25 March to 1 September 2020. [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Light interruption with light slowdown [Part III.B]: short 1-month closure: ordinary sessions of both chambers of the Congress were generally suspended for almost one month (16 March–13 April) due to (i) Resolution 385/2020 of the MHSP, and (ii) a period of adjustment in organizing the implementation of virtual meetings.", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No - ex post [Part II.C].", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes [Part II.C].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Yes. the Congress may repeal, amend or add all the Legislative Decrees enacted by the President [Part I.4].", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No - The Government did not derogate any of the provisions of international conventions. [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Cuba": {"code": "CU", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e42?rskey=LRaAfv&result=1&prd=OXCON", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "01/03/2022"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "No emergency declaration.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A).", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "No [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No - none of them have consisted of a general law providing emergency powers to respond to Covid-19 [Part II.B].", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "No - During the pandemic months of 2020 and the early months of 2021, no elections or referendums were planned to take place in Cuba [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "None", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "No stay-at-home orders for the general population [Part IV.A.1]. Curfews and restrictions to specific segments of population only.", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "\"Light interruption with the postponement of the two annual meetings - 27.", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No - There is no judicial system for the control of constitutionality in Cuba; therefore, none of these legal provisions may be challenged in court on the grounds of unconstitutionality [Part II.C]", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "No - There is no judicial system for the control of constitutionality in Cuba; therefore, none of these legal provisions may be challenged in court on the grounds of unconstitutionality [Part II.C]", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Yes - These legal regulations related to Covid-19 are temporary in nature. In some legal provisions this is express. In other provisions it is deduced by its object of regulation and in others the temporality is subject to compliance with certain recovery phases [Part II.C]", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Hungary": {"code": "HU", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e40", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "03/05/2022"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - 'state of danger' [Part II.A]", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes[Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "Yes - As a result of decisions made exclusively by the Government, with the approval and support of the Parliament, a state of danger was in force between 11 March and 17 June 2020 [Part II.A]", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes - The Government decree declaring the state of danger expires after 15 days, according to the Fundamental Law, if there is no further parliamentary authorisation for its prolongation. [Part II.A]. Later, following the recommendation of the CMO, in response to the Minister’s proposal, the Government declared a state of health crisis on 18 June 2020.46 A state of health care crisis can last for a maximum of six months and is revised every three months, unless the Government extends the measures [Part II.B]", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 1, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No, The basic constitutional arrangements remained intact otherwise [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No COvid-19 specific statute - although two general laws, the so-called Transitional Acts, were introduced, providing emergency powers to respond to Covid-19, laying down certain rules relating to epidemiological measures, and amending certain acts relating to epidemiological measures [Part II.B].", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Yes - By-elections, national and local, and referendums were suspended during the state of danger", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "None", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes - The first restrictions on individual mobility were introduced on 27 March 2020, and the corresponding Government Decree set forth that leaving one’s place of residence or private residence could only take place for essential reasons [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": " ", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes - (...) 50 cases have been brought before the Constitutional Court. Many petitions were rejected on procedural grounds, because the challenged provision was no longer in force at the time of the decision [Part III.B].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Yes - Although the parliamentary control has its apparent limits, since the declaration of the state of danger on 11 March 2020 and as of mid-April 2022, there were 41 interpellations97 and 556 immediate questions98 discussed by Parliament related to the pandemic [Part III.A]", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Yes - In the aftermath of the first wave of the pandemic, some major Acts were amended [Part I].", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No - During the state of danger, the Government did not evoke international conventions or directly quote standards developed by the WHO. [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Malaysia": {"code": "MY", "url": "", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "Forthcoming"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - state of emergency [Part II.A]. 13.\tOn 12 January 2021, the YDPA declared a state of emergency until 1 August 2021. As declared by the Minister of Law on 26 July 2021, the emergency was not extended. ", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes[Part II.A]. ", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "Yes - Such ordinances and the emergency proclamation must be laid before both Houses once they convene, and the ordinances and proclamation would cease to have effect if they are annulled by the Parliament [Part II.B]. However, the proclamation of emergency and suspension of Parliament for almost seven months in 2021 meant it was unable to perform its function of scrutinizing laws that were passed to enforce the government’s Covid-19 management agenda and policies [Part III.A].", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes - On 12 January 2021, the YDPA declared a state of emergency lasting until 1 August 2021 [Part II.A] ", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 7, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "Yes - In January 2021, a state of emergency was declared pursuant to Article 150 of the Federal Constitution on the basis that the pandemic posed  a “threat to the economic life of the nation” [Part I]", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "No [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "Yes - Temporary Measures for Reducing the Impact of Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) Act 2020 [Part II.B]. 17.\tMalaysia’s COVID-19 response has been anchored in two primary legislations: the Prevention and Control of Infectious Diseases Act 1988 (PCID Act) and the Temporary Measures for Reducing the Impact of Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) Act 2020. The latter is a specific legislation introduced to combat the spread of the COVID-19 virus and to mitigate the impact of the pandemic across a variety of issues and sectors. ", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "The government tabled the Temporary Measures for Reducing the Impact of Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) Bill 2020 (“the COVID-19 Bill”) in the Dewan Rakyat on 12 August 2020. The Bill was subsequently passed in the Dewan Rakyat and the Dewan Negara (the Senate) on 25 August 2020 and 22 September 2020, respectively. It received Royal Assent on 23 October 2020. ", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": 13, "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "Yes - The Act would remain in operation for two years from the date of publication, but the Prime Minister may extend the operation of the Act by publishing an order in the Gazette. Under Section 1(3) of the Act, the Prime Minister may exercise such power of extension more than once.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No, but The Amendment Ordinance introduces Part IVA, which strengthens the government’s enforcement powers albeit with implications on fundamental liberties. ", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Yes, suspension - It is worth reiterating again that during the emergency period, the Parliament and state legislative assemblies were suspended [Part III.B]", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "State assembly elections", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yers - on 16 March 2020 the Malaysian government proclaimed a Movement Control Order (MCO), which was to take effect at midnight on 18 March 2020 and continue for two weeks thereafter. The MCO was subsequently extended at two-week intervals and lasted for a total of 8 weeks, before transitioning into the more relaxed Conditional MCO (CMCO) on 4 May 2020, which began the easing of restrictions and the transition into the second phase of Malaysia’s response to the pandemic [Part IV].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Yes.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Yes.The functioning of Parliament has been greatly restricted during the COVID-19 pandemic, especially after the proclamation of emergency in January 2021. It is worth reiterating again at this juncture that during the emergency period, the Parliament and state legislative assemblies were suspended. ", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No - Once proclaimed, the “satisfaction” of the YDPA is immune from judicial review, and courts do not have the jurisdiction to determine the validity of the proclamation or its continued operation [Part II.A}", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Following the first Emergency Ordinance, the government promulgated a series of emergency-related ordinances without parliamentary approval. ", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "No.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No.", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Peru": {"code": "PE", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e39?rskey=vWJA6m&result=28&prd=OCC19", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "31/05/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - state of emergency [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes[Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No - The only condition is that Congress is to be informed. Congress cannot review, let alone revoke the President’s declaration of emergency. Moreover, the state of emergency can be extended through additional decrees [Part II.A].", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes - On 15 March 2020, the President issued Supreme Decree 044-2020-PCM which declared a nationwide state of emergency for 15 days [Part II.A]", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "15 days for state of emergency, 90 days for public health emergency.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "Yes - 'state of emergency' [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes - On 11 March 2020, the Government declared a national public health emergency (Emergencia Sanitaria) for a duration of 90 days [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No - The aforementioned constitutional framework remains unchanged since the start of the pandemic. As of May 2021, there have been no constitutional reforms or modifications implemented in response to the Covid-19 outbreak. [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No - Since the pandemic began, the Government has relied almost exclusively on the powers vested on the executive branch by legislation predating the spread of Covid-19. Within the health sector, the most relevant piece of legislation is the General Health Law [Part II.B]", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No, only limitations are allowed and must comply with constitutional requirements [Part II.A].On one hand, Article 137(1) of the Constitution authorizes the imposition of restrictions on the rights and freedoms previously mentioned (personal freedom and security, inviolability of the home, and freedom of assembly and transit) and allows for the President to call upon the armed forces for help to maintain domestic order. On the other hand, it expressly forbids the banishment of anyone under any circumstance and the restriction of any other fundamental right not listed above.", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "No [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Presidential and Parliamentary elections, Peru (11 April 2021),  Presidential runoff, Peru (6 June 2021), Local municipal elections in Chipao, Ayacucho district, Peru* (10 October 2021).", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes - On 15 March 2020, President Vizcarra declared a state of emergency due to the Covid-19 pandemic and ordered the entire country to stay at home (social isolation) for 15 days, a measure that was renewed several times. [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Yes, two weeks initially, renewed several times [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No - While not legally binding, it is worth noting that the Inter-American Commission on Human Rights guidelines on the protection of human rights during the pandemic were taken into account by the country. Furthermore, the Government has directly quoted the World Health Organization (WHO) on all decrees related to Covid-19. [Part II.A]", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Romania": {"code": "RO", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e38?rskey=vWJA6m&result=31&prd=OCC19", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "19/05/2021"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - state of emergency [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes[Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes - The first, Presidential Decree 195/2020, establishing the state of emergency, entered into force on 16 March 2020, with a 30-day validity period.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 1, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "Yes - 'state of emergency' [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes - 'state of alert' [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "No - Presidential Decrees 195/2020 and 240/2020 explicitly listed the fundamental rights and liberties whose exercise would be restricted on the grounds of public health: freedom of movement, right to respect private and family life, inviolability of the domicile, right to education, freedom of meeting, right to private property, the right to strike, and economic freedom [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Yes - postponement of local elections [Part III.D].", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Local elections, Romania* (27 September 2020), Parliamentary elections, Romania (6 December 2020).", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "No [Part IV.A.1].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "The National Parliament has continued to operate without any limitation [Part III.B]", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No - ex post [Part III.C].", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes - EGO 34/2020 was later declared unconstitutional by Decision of the Constitutional Court No 152/2020 [Part II.A]", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Yes - The measure to prolong the state of emergency was approved with minor additions by Parliament Decision 4/2020. [Part II.A]", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "Yes - the content of the statutes and executive acts adopted during the sanitary crisis did not transpose the recommendations of the WHO exactly as they were formulated by the WHO.", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Sri Lanka": {"code": "LK", "url": "", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "Forthcoming"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No, instrad parliament was dissolved - The President may have been reluctant to declare a state of emergency since doing so would have required the endorsement of Parliament if the state of emergency would require being extended beyond thirty days [Part II.A].", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No - No specific legislation in relation to COVIDCovid-19 was introduced in Sri Lanka. In this context, the primary piece of legislation used to respond to the pandemic was the colonial era legislation made under prerogative legislative powers of the UK Crown (Quarantine and Prevention of Diseases Ordinance of 1897) [Part II.B]", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Yes - postponement of parliamentary elections after its dissolution [Part III.D]. Parliamentary elections, Sri Lanka (originally scheduled for 25 April 2020) moved to 5 August 2020", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Parliamentary elections, Sri Lanka* (5 August 2020).", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "Yes - A country-wide ‘curfew’ was imposed on 27 March 2020 for the purpose of containing the Covid-19 virus. This ‘curfew’ amounted to a total prohibition on the movement of persons, and public gatherings of all kinds. There was significant scepticism surrounding the legality of the ‘curfew’ {Part IV.A]", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "The Parliament had already shifted its activity to online sittings at the beginning of the pandemic [Part III.B]", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No, not mentioned.", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "No, as parliament was dissolved between 2 March and 5 August 2020 [Part III.A].", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "No new individual legislation.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": " No - Sri Lanka has ratified all the main United Nations international human rights conventions  and a range of International Labour Organisation conventions. Following the onset of Covid-19, the Sri Lankan state did not announce any formal derogations in relation to any of these treaties [Part II.A]", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "The European Union": {"code": "EU", "url": "https://oxcon.ouplaw.com/display/10.1093/law-occ19/law-occ19-e35?rskey=vWJA6m&result=11&prd=OCC19", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "16/01/2022"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "No - The EU does not have competence to declare a constitutional state of emergency, in the sense of a normative act that extends powers or suspends provisions concerning the protection of basic rights, the operations of legislatures, and access to courts beyond what is possible and acceptable in normal times [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No - The EU’s response to the Covid-19 pandemic has not altered the basic ‘constitutional’ arrangements detailed above [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No - EU legislature has not formally declared a public health emergency nor has any new general EU law been introduced to respond to the Covid-19 pandemic [Part II.B].", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "NA - The EU is not competent to engage in the restriction of individual mobility by imposing stay-at-home orders or curfews [Part IV.A.I].", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "Yes - On 2 March 2020, the President dissolved the national Parliament, and fixed a Parliamentary election for 25 April 2020. In this context, national-level pParliamentary oversight of Covid-19 policy was virtually absent throughout the critical period of the crisis. NoAs a result, no sitting pParliament functioned during the period between 2 March and 5 August 2020, the critical period of the crisis. The executive branch of government operated without any pParliamentary oversight [Part III.A].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes - The European Parliament also has formal oversight over Commission Decisions through judicial review proceedings [Part III.A].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Tunisia": {"code": "TN", "url": "", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "Forthcoming"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - 'state of emergency' and 'state of exception'. Because of the troubles that occurred during the 2011 revolution and because of terrorist attacks that targeted Tunisia, a state of emergency has been declared several times during the last ten years. The same state of emergency has been used to face the pandemic [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes[Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No - The enactment of the state of emergency does not require the intervention or the approval of the legislative branch [Part II.B].", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Not mentioned", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "\"Yes State of exception declared on 18 March 2020 was based on Article 80 of 2014 Constitution about State of Exception", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "No [Part II.A].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "No - Constitutional rules did not change during the pandemic [Part I].", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No [Part II.B].", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "Municipal in elections in Hassi El Ferid, and Jbeniana, Tunisia (originally scheduled for 28–29 March 2020) moved to 5 July 2020", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Municipal by-elections in Hassi El Ferid, Tunisia* (6 July 2020).", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "\"101.", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "No", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "No - The European Parliament, Council, and Commission continue to function, in modified ways, during the Covid-19 pandemic.", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "No - Measures adopted under emergency powers can be challenged, especially before Administrative Courts. However, because of the pandemic and especially after the total ‘lockdown’ announced on 22 March 2020, courts have been forced to close. This required the Government to enact a legislative decree on 17 April 2020 that suspended the time-limit for instituting the proceedings before the courts [Part II.B]", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "The legislative scrutiny on the delegated powers is ex post, as all the delegated legislative acts must be submitted to the Parliament for approval, within 10 days following the end of the period of delegation [Part III.A]..", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No - No law has derogated from any of the provisions of international conventions [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}, "Venezuela": {"code": "VE", "url": "", "variables": {"1. Date (law as it stood on)": {"date_law_as_it_stood_on": {"title": "Date (law as it stood on)", "answer": "Forthcoming"}, "date_coding_checked_by_rapporteurs": {"title": "Date coding checked by rapporteurs", "answer": "NA."}}, "2. Emergency Declaration": {"emergency_declaration": {"title": "Declaration of emergency", "answer": "Yes - estado de alarma [state of alarm] [Part II.A]. It should be noted that, from 2016 to 2021, that Venezuela maintained , since 14 January 2016, an ongoing state of exception and state of economic emergency pursuant to Article 338 of the Constitution, originally established through Decree Nº 2,184.52 and renewed by more than thirty subsequent decrees.", "question": "Has there been declaration of emergency announced at the national/federal level in response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "rule_making_powers_dependent_emergency": {"title": "Rule-making powers activated by emergency declaration?", "answer": "Yes[Part II.A].", "question": "Were rule-making powers activated by an emergency declaration during the pandemic?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_em_declaration": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - declarations", "answer": "No - Such state of exception shall last for up to 30 days, and may be extended for an additional 30 days upon approval of the National Assembly [Part II.A].", "question": "Was parliamentary approval required and obtained for an emergency declaration made by the executive?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl": {"title": "Sunset provision - emergency declaration", "answer": "Yes - Such state of exception shall last for up to 30 days, and may be extended for an additional 30 days upon approval of the National Assembly [Part II.B].", "question": "Did emergency declarations expire automatically?"}, "sunset_provisions_em_decl_months": {"title": "Duration in months of sunset provisions for emergency declarations", "answer": 1, "question": "If the emergency declaration expired automatically, after how many months?"}, "constitutional_declaration": {"title": "Constitutional", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Has there been a constitutional state of emergency called in the country?"}, "statutory": {"title": "Statutory", "answer": "Yes, 'state of exception' - Making use of the powers conferred by Article 337 of the Constitution, on 13 March 2020, President Maduro declared a national state of exception and alarm through Decree Nº 4,160. [Part II.B].", "question": "Has there been a statutory state of emergency, or analogous measure, declared in the country?"}, "constitutional_changes": {"title": "Constitutional changes", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did the response to the pandemic change the basic constitutional arrangements?"}}, "3. Covid-19 General Statute": {"covid_general_statute": {"title": "Covid-19 general statute", "answer": "No - No other law covering emergency procedures to respond to the Covid-19 pandemic has been enacted by the National Assembly [Part II.B].", "question": "Did the country adopt a general statute specifically to address the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg": {"title": "Fast-tracking Covid-19 specific statute - primary legislation notes", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any new general Covid-19 responsive statute fast-tracked? If fast-tracked, how many sitting days?"}, "fast_tracking_prim_leg_days": {"title": "Fast tracking - Number of sitting days", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Number of parliamentary sitting days from introduction to passage of the bill."}, "party_opposition_covid_statute": {"title": "Political opposition to Covid-19 specific statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was there party political opposition to the adoption of the Covid-19 responsive statute?"}, "amendments_opposition_covid_bill": {"title": "Opposition amendments to Covid responsive bill", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Did the opposition secure amendments to the general Covid-19 responsive bill during legislative scrutiny?"}, "sunset_provisions_statute": {"title": "Sunset provision - statute", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Was any general Covid-19 responsive statute subject to a sunset provision?"}}, "4. Other Emergency Power Issues": {"suspension_bill_rights": {"title": "Suspension of bill of rights", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Has there been a suspension of the bill of rights in the country?"}, "postponement_suspension_elections": {"title": "Suspension/postponement of elections", "answer": "No - Elections in Venezuela were not disrupted as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic.", "question": "Which elections were suspended/postponed, if any?"}, "elections_held": {"title": "Elections Held", "answer": "Parliamentary elections, Venezuela (6 December 2020), Regional and local elections, Venezuela (21 November 2021).1", "question": "Which elections were held between 21 Feb 2020 and 21 Feb 2022?"}, "stay_at_home_orders": {"title": "Stay-at-home orders", "answer": "On 22 March 2020, the President issued a second decree, establishing strict stay-at-home measures. The decree stipulates that, beyond the curfew hours, the circulation of people and vehicles is prohibited on the whole territory of the Republic, and business premises should be closed, except to provide for essential needs or for urgent health purposes\"", "question": "Did any of the national, federal, state-level or local governments issue a stay-at-home order as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic?"}, "sunset_provisions_stay_at_home": {"title": "Sunset provisions - stay at home", "answer": "No.", "question": "Was a sunset provision attached to the stay-at-home order?"}, "parliament_suspension": {"title": "Suspension of parliament", "answer": "No - In the context of the pandemic, the National Assembly held parliamentary sittings virtually in application of its internal rules of procedure and debates [Part III.B].", "question": "Was parliament suspended or closed during the pandemic? "}, "ex_ante_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex ante judicial review", "answer": "No", "question": "Were rule-making powers subject to ex-ante review?"}, "ex_post_judicial_review": {"title": "Ex post judicial review", "answer": "Yes - The law also specifies that the STJ must review the constitutionality of the decree within ten days [Part II.B].", "question": "Were public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments subject to ex post judicial review?"}, "parliament_scrutiny_instrument": {"title": "Parliamentary scrutiny - public health regulations", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Did parliament have the power to veto public health regulations either before or after they were made?"}, "amendment_of_regulations_possible": {"title": "Amendment of regulations possible?", "answer": "Not mentioned.", "question": "Could public health regulations/decrees/statutory instruments be amended by parliament?"}, "sunset_provisions_ind_reg": {"title": "Sunset provision - individual regulations", "answer": "NA.", "question": "Were public health regulations subject to sunset periods?"}, "derogation": {"title": "Derogation", "answer": "No - Ever since the Covid-19 outbreak in 2020, Venezuela has not officially notified the Secretary-General of the United Nations of its decision to derogate from the rights enshrined in the ICCPR as a way to respond to the pandemic. The provisions of the ICCPR have, thus, formally remained fully applicable in Venezuela [Part II.A].", "question": "Did the country derogate from international law in its response to the Covid-19 pandemic?"}}}}}